This back here was my brain cancer.
في الخلفية، تشاهدون الورم السرطاني في دماغي.
Isn't it nice?
ألا يبدوا لطيفًا؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The key phrase is "was,"
الكلمة الرئيسيه هي "كان"
phew.
بكل سرور
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Having brain cancer was really, as you can imagine,
الإصابة بورم سرطاني في الدماغ كما تتخيلون،
shocking news for me.
خبر صادم بالنسبة لي.
I knew nothing about cancer.
لم أكن أعرف شيئاً عن السرطان.
In Western cultures, when you have cancer,
في المجتمعات الغربية، حين تصاب بالسرطان،
it's as if you disappear in a way.
كما لو أنك تختفي بطريقة ما.
Your life as a complex human being is replaced by medical data:
حياتك المعقدة كإنسان، تُستبدل بالبيانات الطبية.
Your images, your exams, your lab values,
صورك، فحوصاتك، تحاليلك المخبرية،
a list of medicines.
قائمه من الأدوية.
And everyone changes as well.
والجميع يتغير بطبيعة الحال.
You suddenly become a disease on legs.
تصبح فجاءه وباء متنقل.
Doctors start speaking a language which you don't understand.
الأطباء يبدأون التحدث بلغة لا تفهمها.
They start pointing their fingers
يبدأون بالإشارة بأصابعهم،
at your body and your images.
إلى جسدك وإلى الصور.
People start changing as well
الناس يبدأون بالتغير أيضاً.
because they start dealing with the disease,
لأنهم يبدأون بالتعامل مع المرض،
instead of with the human being.
بدلاً من التعامل مع أصحاب المرض.
They say, "What did the doctor say?"
يقولون: "ماذا قال الأطباء؟"
before even saying, "Hello."
قبل حتى أن يقولوا "مرحباً".
And in the meanwhile,
وأيضاً في ذات الحين،
you're left with questions to which nobody gives an answer.
تكون محملاً بأسئلة لا أحد يعطي جوابا لها.
These are the "Can I?" questions:
وهي أسئلة "هل أستطيع؟ ":
Can I work while I have cancer?
هل أستطيع العمل وأنا مصاب بالسرطان؟
Can I study? Can I make love? Can I be creative?
هل أستطيع الدراسة؟ هل أستطيع ممارسة بالحب؟ أن أكون مبدعاً؟
And you wonder, "What have I done to deserve this?"
وتبدأ بالتساؤل، " ماذا فعلته لأستحق ذلك؟".
You wonder, "Can I change something about my lifestyle?"
تتساءل، " هل أستطيع تغيير شيء في نظام حياتي؟".
You wonder, "Can I do something?
تتساءل، "هل أستطيع فعل شيء ما؟
Are there any other options?"
هل هناك خيارات أخرى؟"
And, obviously, doctors are the good guys in all these scenarios,
وبالتاكيد، الأطباء هم الأفضل في هذه السيناريوهات.
because they are very professional and dedicated to curing you.
لأنهم محترفين ومكرسين أنفسهم لأجل شفائك.
But they also are very used to having to deal with patients,
ولكنهم أيضاً ملزمين بالتعامل مع المرضى،
so I'd say that they sometimes lose the idea that this is torture for you
لذلك أقول أنهم أحيانا ينسون فكرة أن هذا الوضع هو تعذيب لك،
and that you become, literally, a patient --
وأن تتحول حرفياً إلى مريض.
"patient" means "the one who waits."
"مريض" بمعنى " الشخص الذي ينتظر".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
they tend to not engage you in any way to learn about your condition,
تميل بطريقة لا تساعدك على فهم حالتك،
to get your friends and family engaged,
ولاتساعد عائلتك وأصدقائك للمشاركة،
or showing you ways in which you can change your lifestyle
أو تحثك بطريقة تمكنك من تغيير نظام حياتك،
to minimize the risks of what you're going through.
للحد من المخاطر التي تعايشها.
But instead, you're forced there to wait
وبدلاً من ذلك، تُجبر على الأنتظار،
in the hands of a series of very professional strangers.
بين يدي مجموعة من مهنيين غرباء .
While I was in the hospital,
أثناء مكوثي في المستشفى،
I asked for a printed-out picture of my cancer
طلبت صورة مطبوعه للورم،
and I spoke with it.
وقمت بالتحدث معها.
It was really hard to obtain,
كان الحصول عليها صعب للغاية،
because it's not common practice to ask for a picture of your own cancer.
لأنه ليس معتاداً أن تطلب صورة للورم السرطاني.
I talked to it and I said,
تحدث إلى الصورة وقلت،
"Okay, cancer, you're not all there is to me.
"حسناً، أيها السرطان، أنت لست كل ما يهمني.
There's more to me.
هناك ما يهمني بدرجة أكبر.
A cure, whichever it is, will have to deal with the whole of me."
العلاج، مهما سيكون، سيحتاج إلى التعامل معي كلياً".
And so, the next day, I left the hospital against medical advice.
حينها، في اليوم التالي، غادرت المشفى، مخالفاً النصيحة الطبية.
I was determined to change my relationship with the cancer
كنت عازما على تغيير علاقتي مع السرطان
and I was determined to learn more about my cancer
وكنت عازماً على التعلم أكثر عن ورمي السرطاني
before doing anything as drastic as a surgery.
قبل أن أقدم على فعل شيء جذري كالجراحة.
I'm an artist, I use several forms of open-source technologies
أنا فنان، أستخدم العديد من أشكال التقنيات ذات المصادر المفتوحة
and open information in my practice.
والمعلومات العامة في عروضي.
So my best bet was to get it all out there, get the information out there,
لذا فأفضل ما يمكن القيام به هو الحصول على المعلومات المتوفرة،
and use it so that it could be accessed by anyone.
واستخدامها بحيث تكون متاحة للجميع.
So I created a website, which is called La Cura,
لذا قمت بإنشاء موقع الكتروني، يدعى"لآ كورا"
on which I put my medical data, online.
قمت فيه بنشر بياناتي الطبية.
I actually had to hack it
في الحقيقة اضطررت لأختراقه،
and that's a thing which we can talk about in another speech.
وهو مجال آخر للحديث عنه في حديث آخر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I chose this word, La Cura --
اخترت هذه الكلمة "لآكورا"
La Cura in Italian means "the cure" --
هي كلمة إيطالية وتعني العلاج
because in many different cultures,
لأنه في العديد من الثقافات
the word "cure" can mean many different things.
كلمه "علاج" قد تعني عدة أشياء مختلفة.
In our Western cultures,
في ثقافتنا الغربية،
it means eradicating or reversing a disease,
تعني القضاء على، أو مجابهة المرض،
but in different cultures,
ولكن في ثقافات أخرى،
for example, a culture from Asia,
مثلاً، في آسيا،
from the Mediterranean, from Latin countries, from Africa,
من دول البحر المتوسط، من الدول اللاتينية، في أفريقيا
it can mean many more things.
ممكن أن تعني عدة أشياء
Of course, I was interested in the opinions of doctors
بالطبع، كنت مهتماً برأي الأطباء
and healthcare providers,
ومتخصصي الخدمات الطبية
but I was also interested in the cure of the artist, of the poet,
ولكني كنت مهتما بعلاج الفنان، الشاعر،
of, who knows, the musicians.
و آخرين، كالموسيقيين.
I was interested in the social cure,
كنت مهتماً بالعلاج الإجتماعي،
I was interested in the psychological cure,
كنت مهتماً بالعلاج النفسي،
I was interested in the spiritual cure,
كنت مهتماً بالعلاج الروحاني،
I was interested in the emotional cure,
كنت مهتماً بالعلاج العاطفي،
I was interested in any form of cure.
كنت مهتماً بأي شكل من أشكال العلاج.
And, it worked.
و قد نجح ذلك.
The La Cura website went viral.
الموقع الإكتروني إنتشر سريعاً.
I received lots of media attention from Italy and from abroad
تلقيت الكثير من إهتمام الإعلام من إيطاليا وغيرها،
and I quickly received more than 500,000 contacts --
وحصلت سريعاً على أكثر من 500,000 جهة إتصال
emails, social networking --
رسائل من مواقع التواصل الإجتماعي
most of them were a suggestion on how to cure my cancer,
العديد منها كان إقتراحات لكيفية علاج الورم
but more of them were about how to cure myself
ولكن الأكثر كان عن العلاج الذاتي
as a full individual.
كفرد كامل.
For example, many thousands of videos,
مثلاً،
images, pictures, art performances
عدة آلاف من الفيديوهات،
were produced for La Cura.
تم انتاجها لموقع "لآ كورا".
For example, here we see Francesca Fini in her performance.
مثلاً، هنا تشاهدون "فرانسيسكا فيني" في آدائها.
Or, as artist Patrick Lichty has done:
أو كما فعل الفنان "باتريك ليتشتي":
He produced a 3D sculpture of my tumor
قام بطباعة نموذج ثلاثي الأبعاد للورم،
and put it on sale on Thingiverse.
وعرضة للبيع في موقع Thingiverse.
Now you can have my cancer, too!
الآن، يمكنكم الحصول على ورمي، أيضاً!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Which is a nice thing, if you think about it,
وهو شيء لطيف، إذا فكرت بذلك،
we can share our cancer.
يمكننا مشاركة أورامنا السرطانية.
And this was going on --
واستمر ذلك،
scientists, the traditional medicine experts,
العلماء، خبراء العلاج التقليدي،
several researchers, doctors --
العديد من الباحثين، الأطباء،
all connected with me to give advice.
الجميع تواصل معي لإبداء النصح.
With all this information and support,
ومع هذا الكم من المعلومات والدعم،
I was able to form a team of several neurosurgeons,
كنت قادراً على جمع فريق
traditional doctors,
وأطباء تقليديين،
oncologists, and several hundred volunteers
أخصائيي الأورام،
with whom I was able to discuss
والذين استطعت النقاش معهم
the information I was receiving, which is very important.
عن المعلومات التي كانت تصلني،
And together, we were able to form a strategy for my own cure
وجميعاً، كنا قادرين على
in many languages, according to many cultures.
من عدة لغات، وذلك لإختلاف الثقافات.
And the current strategy spans the whole world
وهذه الخطة امتدت حول العالم كله،
and thousands of years of human history,
وعبر آلاف السنوات من تاريخ البشرية،
which is quite remarkable for me.
وذلك كان رائعاً جدا بالنسبة لي.
[Surgery]
[العملية الجراحية]
The follow-up MRIs showed, luckily, little to no growth of the cancer.
صور الرنين المغناطيسية اللاحقة أظهرت،
So I was able to take my time and choose.
مما أتاح لي المزيد من الوقت لإتخاذ القرار.
I chose the doctor I wanted to work with,
اخترت الطبيب الذي أردت التعامل معه،
I chose the hospital I wanted to stay in,
اخترت المشفى الذي أردت البقاء فيه،
and in the meanwhile, I was supported by thousands of people,
وأثناء ذلك، هناك آلاف من الناس تدعمني،
none of whom felt pity for me.
والذين لم يكونوا بموقف الشفقة.
Everyone felt like they could take an active role
جميعهم شعروا أن لهم دور نشط يقومون به
in helping me to get well,
لمساعدتي على التحسن،
and this was the most important part of La Cura.
وهذا هو الجزء الأهم من موقع "لآ كورا".
What are the outcomes?
ماهي النتائج؟
I'm fine, as you can see, pretty fine.
أنا بخير، كما تشاهدون، بصحة جيدة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I had excellent news
أحمل لكم أخبار ممتازة:
after the surgery --
بعد الجراحة،
which is a "good" kind of cancer which doesn't grow a lot.
وهو ورم حميد ولا ينمو بكثافة.
I have completely changed my life and my lifestyle.
قمت بتغيير كامل لحياتي ولنظامي.
Everything I did was thoughtfully designed to get me engaged.
كل شيء كان مخططاً ليتيح لي المشاركة.
Up until the very last few minutes of the surgery,
حتى الدقائق ماقبل الجراحة،
which was very intense,
والتي كانت حساسة،
a matrix of electrodes was implanted in my brain
مجموعة من الأقطاب الكهربائيه تم زرعها في دماغي
from this side,
هذا الجانب،
to be able to build a functional map of what the brain controls.
حتى تستطيع إنشاء خريطة وظيفية
And right before the operation,
وقبل العملية مباشرة،
we were able to discuss the functional map of my brain
كنا قادرين على مناقشة
with the doctor, to understand which risks I was running into
مع الطبيب، لفهم أي مخاطر قد أواجهها
and if there were any I wanted to avoid.
وإذا كنت أريد تحاشي أي منها.
Obviously, there were.
بالطبع، كان هناك العديد.
[Open]
[الإنفتاح]
Thousands of people shared their stories, their experiences.
آلاف الناس شاركوا قصصهم و تجاربهم.
Doctors got to talk with people they don't usually consult
الأطباء أمكنهم التحدث مع
I'm a self-founding, continuous state of translation
أنا بنيت نفسي ذاتياً، بالاعتماد على الترجمة
among many different languages,
من مختلف اللغات.
in which science meets emotion
بطريقة حيث العلم يلتقي بالمشاعر
and conventional research meets traditional research.
والبحوث التقليدية تجتمع بالأبحاث التقليدية.
[Society]
[المجتمع]
was to feel like a part of a really engaged and connected society
كان توفير الشعور بأنك
whose wellness really depends on the wellness of all of its components.
والذي كانت صحته تعتمد حقاً
This global performance is my open-source cure for cancer.
هذا الآداء العالمي هو علاجي ذو المصدر المفتوح للسرطان.
And from what I feel,
ومن خلال ما أشعر به،
it's a cure for me, but for us all.
إنه علاج لي، ولكنه للجميع أيضاً.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause).
(تصفيق)